<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Maine grounds of religion vvithout the knowledge whereof none may presume to come to the Lords table here, or expect to communicate with him in glory hereafter : collected out of a more copious   catechisme, and published especially for the benefit of such poore soules as want either money to buy, or time to learne, or memories to retain [brace] a larger treatise.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12402A.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4686</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23737624</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23737624</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26848</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02270)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26848)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1833:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Maine grounds of religion vvithout the knowledge whereof none may presume to come to the Lords table here, or expect to communicate with him in glory hereafter : collected out of a more copious   catechisme, and published especially for the benefit of such poore soules as want either money to buy, or time to learne, or memories to retain [brace] a larger treatise.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones and are to be solde by Francis Coules dwelling in the Old Bayly, neere to Newgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26848:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26848:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <p>RELIGION.</p>
            <p>VVithout the knowledge whereof none may preſume to come to the Lords Table here or expect to communicate with him in glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>Collected out of a more copious Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, and publiſhed eſpecially for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of ſuch poore Soules, as want:
<list>
                  <item>Either money to buy,</item>
                  <item>Or time to learne,</item>
                  <item>Or memories to retaine</item>
               </list>
a larger Treatiſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEB. 5.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When for the time ye ought to be Teachers, yee haue need that one teach you againe, which be the firſt Principles of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of God, and are become ſuch as haue need of milk, and not of ſtrong meate.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM IONES, and are to be ſolde by <hi>Francis Coules</hi> dwelling in the Old Bayly, neere to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="parents" type="precept">
            <pb facs="tcp:26848:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>A Precept for Parents.</head>
            <q>
               <p>Theſe words which I command thee this day ſhall be in thine heart: and thou ſhalt teach them diligently unto thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſhalt talke of them when thou ſitteſt in thine houſe, and when thou wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt by the way, and when thou lyeſt downe, and when thou riſeſt vp.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6, 7.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="children and servants" type="precept">
            <head>To Children and Servants.</head>
            <q>
               <p>Sanctifie the Lord God in your hearts, and be ready alwayes to giue an anſwer to every man that asketh you a reaſon of of the hope that is in you, with meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and feare.</p> 
               <bibl>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:26848:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>THE MAINE GROVNDS OF RELIGION.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <hi>OF what Religion are you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſwer.</label>
Of the Chriſtian Religion.<note place="margin">Acts 11, 24</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What Religion is that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 4, 12.</note> That which teacheth men to looke for true and euerlaſting happineſſe by Chriſt alone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Where is this Religion taught?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim: 3, 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What may wee learne out of the Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two things:<note place="margin">Iohn 17, 3 Eccle: 7, 29</note> the knowledge of God, and of our ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are wee taught concerning God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That there are thrée Perſons,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 5, 7 Prov. 16, 4 Mat: 10, 29</note> yes but one God, who is the Ordainer, the Maker, and Gouernour of all things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
               <hi>Q. What are we taught concer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> our ſelues?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1 26.. and 3, 1, 2. Rom. 5.12</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> That Man and Woman bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> made in the Image of God, fell from the bleſſed eſtate, and became moſt curſed Creatures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is then the eſtate of every naturall man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.3. Rom. 7.24</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Very miſerable, and in no wiſe to be reſted in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What maketh his eſtate ſo bad?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 59.2. Rom. 6.23</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two things: Sinne and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What call you Sinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.4.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Euery breach of Gods Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How doth man breake the Law of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 1 15.16, 17. and 64.6.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> By doing things forbidden, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing things commanded, or failing in the manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the puniſhment of ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28.15. Luk 16 22 23</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> All miſeries in this life, death in the end, and hell euer after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is ſinne ſuch a grieuous thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea, it is the moſt hainous and loathſome thing in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How appeareth that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.31 and 12.29</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Both by the puniſhment, and by the perſon againſt whom it is committed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
               <hi>Q. Who is that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Almighty God, whoſe Holineſſe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pſa 36, 5, 6</note>
Power, Iuſtice and Goodneſſe is infinite and vnſpeakable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What ſhall a man doe in that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Bewaile his miſery,<note place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> and haſten to get out of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is he able of himſelfe to doe this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: and beſides he hath thrée ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the fleſh, the Deuill, and the world,<note place="margin">2 Cor, 3:5 Eph. 6.12.</note>
that will labour to holde him in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Where ſhall a man finde help?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Onely in Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 146.</note> the onely begotten Sonne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What hath he done to deliuer man out of miſery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He became man and in our nature fully ſatiſfied the Law &amp; Iuſtice of God.<note place="margin">Gal. 4.4, 5</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q How hath he done this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> By bearing for vs the puniſhment which the Law threatneth;<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13. Mat. 3.15.</note> and fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the righteouſneſſe which the Law requireth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q How did Chriſt beare the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due to ſinne by the Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> By enduring manifold miſeries all his life time, and in the end the wrath of God, and the curſed death of the Croſſe.<note place="margin">Luk. 9.58. Phil. 2.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
               <hi>Q. How did he worke the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe requyred by the Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By being obedient to the will of God,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2, 22 Iohn 4, 34</note> in thought, word, and doed, all his life long.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What benefit haue we by Chriſt his death and ſufferings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2, 14, 15.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Deliuerance from ſinne, and the puniſhment thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. And why by his righteouſneſſe and obedience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5, 18 19, 11.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> The fauour of God, and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How may we obtaine theſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits by Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 1, 12.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> Onely by true faith in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is a true Faith in Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1, 16 Iohn 6, 69 2 Tim 2, 12</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a beliefe of the Goſpell, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a man doth truely reſt, and caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vpon Chriſt alone, for remiſſion of ſinnes, and eternall ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is it in our power to beleeue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2, 8 Gal: 5, 22 Rom. 10, 17.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: it is the gift of God, by the working of the Spirit, throgh the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Shall all beleevers haue benefit by Chriſts death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All that truely beléeue ſhall: but there is a dead faith that profiteth no thing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
               <hi>Q. How is the true faith perceived?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the fruits thereof,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3, 3</note> and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe whereſoeuer Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit worketh true Faith,<note place="margin">Acts 15, 5</note> there he work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth repentance alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such a change of the heart,<note place="margin">Rom: 12, 2</note> as bringeth forth a reformed life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Whence commeth this change?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Eſpecially from the ſight and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods mercy towards vs in Chriſt.<note place="margin">1 Ioh: 4, 19</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. From what is the heart changed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> From the loue of the world to the loue of God:<note place="margin">1 Ioh: 2, 15 Tit: 2, 12</note> from careleſnes to conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and deſire to pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the change called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is called in Scripture a new creature.<note place="margin">2 Cor: 5, 17</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How doth it appeare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When in word and déed wée en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoure to abſtaine from euill,<note place="margin">Eſ: 1, 16, 17 Eph. 4, 21 23, 24.</note> and to exerciſe our ſelues in that which is gold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is this change of heart and minde perfect in any?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: we beléeue not perfectly,<note place="margin">Mark: 2, 24 1 Cor: 13, 9 Heb: 6, 1.</note> and therefore wée cannot loue perfectly, but wée muſt ſtriue to perfection.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2, 2: 1 The 5, 17 20, 19, &amp;c:</note>
               <hi>Q How muſt we ſtriue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> By a diligent vſe of the mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> which God hath appointed for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in faith and repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are the publike meanes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are chiefly thrée: hearing the word,<note place="margin">Luc: 22, 19 Ro: 10, 13, 14,</note> receiuing the Sacrament, and ioyning in Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q What are the Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ro: 4, 11: 1 Cor: 10: 16;</note>
               <hi>A</hi> Certaine outward ſignes and ſeale appointed of God, to aſſure vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt and all his benefits are giuen to vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q How many Sacraments are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor: 10, 32, 34,</note>
               <hi>A</hi> Two, Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q What doth Baptiſme aſſure vs of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> That being ingrafted into Chriſt; wée are waſhed from our ſinnes in his blood,<note place="margin">Gal: 3, 27: Tit: 3, 5:</note> and borne anew in God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q What doth the Lords Supper aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor: 11 24 Ioh: 6, 54,</note>
               <hi>A</hi> It doeth further warrant vs that Chriſt is giuen to vs to be our ſpirituall nouriſhment to euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q Who maketh the right vſe of the Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat, 26: 28 Gal. 6, 15,</note>
               <hi>A</hi> He that is thereby daily confirmed in faith and newnes of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q Who obtaine this benefit by the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
               <hi>A</hi> Such as come with knowledge,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11, 28.</note>
faith, repentance and loue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Acrauing of thoſe things at Gods hands which wée want,<note place="margin">Pſa. 50.15 Phil: 4.6.</note> and thanking him for thoſe we haue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. When doe men pray a right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> When they pray onely to God,<note place="margin">Ioh: 16.23 Iam, 4, 3,</note> in the name of Chriſt: asking things law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to his glory, with faith, féeling and loue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What be the private meanes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Reading and praying both alone,<note place="margin">Deut, 17, 19 Mat. 7, 7 Gen 18, 19 and 24, 63 1 The, 5, 11 Pſa, 119, 9</note> and with others inſtructing our families, thinking vpon good matters, admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and comforting one another, &amp; wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ouer our owne wayes according to the word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q What will the right vſe of all theſe meanes work in Gods children?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> A moſt happy and comfortable change, from that which they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, euen in this life.<note place="margin">Acts 26, 18 1 Co, 6, 11</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q What becommeth of them after this life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> The ſoule goeth immediately into the Paradiſe of God, and the body ſhall be raiſed vp at the laſt day,<note place="margin">Luk, 19, 22 1 Cor, 16.52. Mat 25, 46</note> and ioyned with the ſame in glory for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
               <hi>Q. What is the portion of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant or prophane perſons, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne theſe meanes of grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Deu: 28, 20 65, 66, 67 2 Theſ: 1, 9 Luke 13, 8 Mat: 25, 41 &amp; 13, 49, 50.</note>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are in a moſt curſed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion while they liue héere, and hereafter they ſhall be baniſhed from the joyes of heauen, and ſhall for euermore bee tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with the Deuill in Hell, when is wéeping and wailing, and gnaſhing of téeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <pb facs="tcp:26848:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
            <head>Certaine Rules for the direction of a Chriſtian life, expreſſed in Meeter, for helpe to the memory.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>A</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Prov: 4, 2 Luk: 21, 3 Ioſu: 7, 21 Gen: 39, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>ACquaint thy ſelfe most narrowly,</l>
               <l>Thy mind, thy heart, and life to watch:</l>
               <l>Lest idle thoughts and noyſome dreames,</l>
               <l>Doe wicked lusts and dealings hatch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>B</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Eph: 5, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal: 90, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mat: 6, 33 Luk: 10, 41</note>Be wiſe and carefull to redeeme,</l>
               <l>Thy precious time to holy deedes:</l>
               <l>Let not theſe earthly matters baſe,</l>
               <l>Conſume more houres than thou muſt needs</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>C</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal: 52, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dan: 6, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal: 6.6. &amp; 4, 4, 8</note>Call to thy minde when night is come,</l>
               <l>Thy ſinnes that day to crave releaſe:</l>
               <l>Thinke on Gods favours him to prayſe,</l>
               <l>That ſo thou maist lie downe in peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>D</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Gen: 18, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Psa: 27, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; 90, 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 15, 16, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>Doth morne approach and ſleepe depart,</l>
               <l>First lift thy heart to God on high:</l>
               <l>Commit thy ſelfe and wayes to him,</l>
               <l>And vowe to ſerve him faithfully.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
               <head>E</head>
               <l>Enter vpon no kinde of worke,</l>
               <l>But craue Gods Spirit thee to protect:</l>
               <l>Goe to no place or company,</l>
               <l>But pray from ill mee to direct.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>F</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim, 4, 5 1 Cor, 10 1: Mat, 14 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6 and 26 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6</note>Forget not when thou meanſt to vſe,</l>
               <l>Gods creatures, or his mercy ſweete:</l>
               <l>For ſoules delight, or bodies health,</l>
               <l>To craue his leaue and bleſſing meete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>G</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Deu, 8, 10 and 32, 15 Pſa, 68, 19 Mat: 16, 30</note>Giue vnto God due thanks and praiſe,</l>
               <l>When comfortable vſe thou haſt:</l>
               <l>Or any of his bleſſings good,</l>
               <l>Or elſe he counts them ſpent in waſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>H</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh, 4, 24 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sam, 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3 Pſ, 5, 2 and 30, 11</note>Hold this for ſure, that in true prayer,</l>
               <l>The hearts deſire is chiefeſt thing:</l>
               <l>Yet voice will help the ſame to warme,</l>
               <l>And baniſh dulneſſe and wandring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>I</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Gen, 24, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3, Dan, 6 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0, Psa, 55, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7, and 19, 164</note>(If poſſibly thou canſt it finde)</l>
               <l>Set out ſome time of euery day:</l>
               <l>To muſe, to pray, and reade good bookes,</l>
               <l>That grace and conſcience increaſe may.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>K</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Prov, 16, 4 Mat, 10, 29 Eccleſ, 9, 2 Mat, 25, 33</note>Keep heart and minde much bent to thinke</l>
               <l>How God hath made and ruleth all:</l>
               <l>How here he deales with good and bad,</l>
               <l>How differ in the end they ſhall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
               <head>L</head>
               <l>Like beſt to ponder Christ his workes,<note place="margin">Rom, 5, 2 1 Cor, 2, Gal, 6, 14, Phil, 3, 8,</note>
               </l>
               <l>How he thee ſau'd from ſinne and ſhame:</l>
               <l>And made thee heire of Paradiſe,</l>
               <l>Delight therein and praiſe his name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>M</head>
               <l>Marke well the liues of good and bad,<note place="margin">Eſa, 37, 37 Mat. 25, 26 Luk, 16, 23 Iam, 5, 10</note>
               </l>
               <l>Conſider eke the ends of both:</l>
               <l>To moue thee for to imitate,</l>
               <l>The vertuous man, and ſinners loath.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>N</head>
               <l>Nurture thy ſoule with thoughts of death,<note place="margin">Pſa, 39.4 Heb, 9, 27, Luke, 12, 20 Col, 3, 1</note>
               </l>
               <l>That needs thou muſt from hence remoue:</l>
               <l>(Leauing thy wealth and deareſt things)</l>
               <l>To fixe thy minde on heauen aboue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>O</head>
               <l>Obſerue how thy corruption dyes,<note place="margin">Gal, 6, 14 Iob 20, 12 Mat, 5, 29 and 16, 2</note>
               </l>
               <l>Let not thy deareſt friend deceiue thee:</l>
               <l>Why ſhouldſt thou count that ſweet and good,</l>
               <l>Which may of glory quite bereaue thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>P</head>
               <l>Practiſe Gods worſhip with delight,<note place="margin">Deu, 28, 47 Pſa, 16, 3 and 116, 10 2 Co, 7, 11</note>
               </l>
               <l>Ioy in the godlies company:</l>
               <l>VVith God thy couenant oft renew,</l>
               <l>Mourne for thy ſinne, and it defie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Q</head>
               <l>Quench not thine owne and others Spirit,<note place="margin">1 The, 5, 19 Eph, 4, 19 Eze, 13, 22 Mat, 5, 6</note>
               </l>
               <l>All idle or vnſauory speech:</l>
               <l>By thy behaviour euery where,</l>
               <l>Let good, no ill to others teach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
               <head>R</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Exod: 20, 7 Deu: 28, 58 Pſal: 15, 3 Mat: 5, 44</note>Rehearſe no name, no worke, nor word</l>
               <l>Of God, without high reverence:</l>
               <l>Speake of no man but lovingly,</l>
               <l>Although it be in thy defence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>S</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Act: 24, 16 Eph: 5, 22, 25. &amp; 6, 1, 4, 5, 6.</note>Seeke to approove thy ſelfe to God,</l>
               <l>Thy conſcience, and Gods children deare</l>
               <l>By dealing in thy calling, and</l>
               <l>With ſuch to whom thou art most neare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>T</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Eph: 6, 12 Ier: 17, 9 2 Tim: 3, 5 Rev: 3, 16</note>Take heede lest Satans craft (by meanes</l>
               <l>Of natures bent t'hypocriſie,</l>
               <l>And to profaneſſe) make thee uſe</l>
               <l>Religious duties formally.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>V</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Mat: 15, 8, &amp; 10, 28, &amp; 6, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note>Vſe not the ſame for faſhions ſake,</l>
               <l>Or for thy credit, but with care</l>
               <l>Thy God to pleaſe, that in the end</l>
               <l>Both ſoule and body well may fare.</l>
            </lg>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7.</bibl>
               <p>Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord give thee underſtanding in all things.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <div n="before eating" type="grace">
               <pb facs="tcp:26848:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
               <head>Grace before meate.</head>
               <p>Moſt gracious God and louing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we humbly beſeech thée to forgiue vs all our ſinnes. Be preſent with vs, and bleſſe vs, and thy good creatures pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for vs. Giue vs grace to receiue them thankefully as from thy hand, and to vſe them ſoberly as in thy ſight, is thy glory and our owne comfort, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="after eating" type="grace">
               <head>Grace after meate.</head>
               <p>We humbly thanke thée, O Lord hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, for refreſhing our fraile bodies with thy good creatures, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee likewiſe to feed our ſoules with thy liuely word, that we may glorifie thée, both with our ſoules and with our bodies through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>Bleſſe good Lord thy holy Church, our gracious King, his Royall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie and Realme, and ſend vs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
